<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cort verhael van den aenslach gheschiedt in Irlandt door sommighe wederspannighe teghen Enghel landt, de welcke verslagen zijn gheweest int jaer M.D.L.XXIX. in der maendt van Julius.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841288</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5862</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04114)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5862)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 571:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cort verhael van den aenslach gheschiedt in Irlandt door sommighe wederspannighe teghen Enghel landt, de welcke verslagen zijn gheweest int jaer M.D.L.XXIX. in der maendt van Julius.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londen [i.e. Antwerp?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>int jaer M.D.L.XXIX.] [1579]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual place of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="dut">dut</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1558-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="dut">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5862:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5862:1"/>
            <head>Cort verhael van den aen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlach gheſchiedt in Irlandt / door ſommighe wederſpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nighe reghen Enghel landt / de welcke verſlagen zijn ghe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeſt int jaer M.D.LXXIX. in de maendt van Iulius.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Euen yeghelijchen is kennelijck ghenoech / hoc dat nae de aflyuicheyt van Coninghinne Marie / zijn op<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtaen booſe gheeſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / die niet anders en hebben gheſoecht dan die Conin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghinne Elizabeth / nu teghenwoordichlijch in Enghel-landt regnerende / te ſluyten wt de wettelicke erf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feniſſe des Coninck rijcks / dick ende menich mael onder malckanderen practiſerende looſe liſten / laghen ende von<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den / om de goede onderſaeten in roere te ſtellen / ende de wapen te doen aen neme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teghen de voorſeyde Coninghin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: ende dit al door het ingheuen ende toeſtoken van vecl gheeſtelijcke perſoonen ende vluchtighe edel lieden / ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willicht tor alſulche daedt door het hof van Roome / welck niet op en houdt alle Coninck rijcken ende landen / die van de Roomſche heerſchappije zijn afgheweken / tot oproer ende werringhe te brenghen: de ſelue door g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewoonlijcke Pauſche gheweldicheyt ouergeuende den ghene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die noch recht noch verſter<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eniſſe daer aen en hebben / fae verlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nende volle af-laeten allen den ghenen die met alſulcken volck aenſpannen tot haeren vercrijghe / teghen alle ghee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelijcke ende weerel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lijcke rechte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Alſoo my lichtelick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen
<pb facs="tcp:5862:2"/>bemercken een tghene dat onlan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s is gheſchiedt in Irlandt: Waer af ick hier een cort verhael ſal maecken: den o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pronck verclarende vanden aenſlach die te Roome is beworpen gheweeſt door eene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Enghelſ-man ghenaemt Capiteyn Stuckley int iaer M.D.Lxxvij. in December.</p>
            <p>Te weien: Ter ſchier tnt als don Ian looſſelijck in ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomen hadde het caſteel van Name / ſoo hebben de ballin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen wt Enghel landt die alſ doen te Roome ende in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nien waere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / bene erſticht te verwecken ſommighe ſchalcke en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behendighe Capiteynen / om de wapen aen te nemen / ende alſulcke macht te vergaederen als hen moghelijck waere / om te ouervallen ende in te nemen de Eyl landen daer Eſcouedo vermaen af maect / ghelijck als hy onder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſen ende onderricht was door het hooch hof va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alle ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raders / hopende met alſulcken middel ghemackelicker de Neder-landen in bedwanck te brenghen / de welcke af-val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lich waeren gheworden teghen don Ian van Ooſtenrijck / ter ſaecken van de opghenomene brieuen / waer door alle zijn venijn ende alle de aenſlaeghen der ghener die hy te wercke hadde gheſtelt / openbaer ende blijckelijck zijn ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worden. Tot deſen bedrijue heeft hem de voorſeyde Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn Stuckley veerdich ghemaect met ſommighe ſoldate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die hy daer aen nam / om Irlandt te ouervallen / terwijle dat don Ian met het crijchſ volck welck van daghe te da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe wt I taken quam tot ſijuer hulpen / ſoude orloghen te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen de Staten van Nederlandt: hoe-wel dat ſommighe gheenſ-ſins en dachten dat het op Irlandt ghedijde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoude. De voorſeyde Capiteyn is t'ſchepe gheg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en in de ſtadt ghenae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Ciuita Vecchia</hi> ghelegen op de zee / ontrent twaelf oft derthien mijlen van Roome: ende den roep giuck doen ter tijdt / dat hy ſoude aen comen te Genua / Calis / Liſbone ende in Vranckrijck / ende daer ouer alhem ſterck maken ende verſien van crijchſ-volck / munitien ende victalien:
<pb facs="tcp:5862:2"/>welck oock warachtich ſcheen te wefen: Want als hy aen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghecomen was in Portegael te Liſbone / ende des Conincs armeye al gereedt was om t'ſeyl te gaen nae Barbarien / <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo voeghde hy hem daer by / en<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſtercte den hoop met <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ijnen volcke / hem gantſchelijck ſtellende tot des Conincks dienſt / hopende door dit middel ghemackelijcker te comen tot zijn vermeten / achter dat hy hem beter verſien hadde <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an ghelde / ende van volcke welck hy noch met der tijdt tzijner begheerten ſoude betrecken: daer en houen oock hopende dat zijn volck / welck hy aenghenome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hadde / dies te geſchicter ende vromer ſoude weſen / naedemaei dat het met alſulcke armeye aengheſpannen was. Maer midts dat de fortune haer ter contrarien heeft ghekeert / ende dat de voorghenoemde. Stuckley verſlaghen is gheweeſt in den ſlach teghen de Mooren: ſoo heeft zijn Lieu-tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naemt Mac Moris / met de reſte van wolck dat hy tſamen mocht vergaederen / ende met de ghene die in Spanien veerdich waren om in zijn gheſelſchap te comen / den ierſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aenſlach wederom verſoecht / ende is in demae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dt van Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius leſtleden int faer M.D.LXXIX. onerghecomen met ontrent duſent mannen tot in Irlandt / int groot rimer gheleghen op de zyde van Spanien.</p>
            <p>Een Biſſchop die met hem was ghecomen / nam de voor-togt op d'landt: daer nae volgden de cruycen / vanen ende monicken: Doorts hebben zy volck tot haeren dienſt ghe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onden / de welcke des nachts vier maecten / om den wech tot henwaerts te wijſen / op dat ſy ſouden moghen aen-comen: want by daghe werden ſy van d'Engheliche belet. Maer ten laughen leſten / doen ſy haerlieder opſet niet en couſten volvrenghen / ſoo zijn ſy al verſtroyt ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morden / ende de voorſeyde Mac Moris is verſlaeghen gheweeſt van tvolck vanden ſeluen lande diet met de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninghinne hielden: welck gheſchiedde err dat de thien du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:5862:3"/>marmen aenghecomen waeren / die de Coninghin<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> daerwaerts gheſonden hadde / om den hoop te verniele</p>
            <p>Hier aen ſien my merckelijck / hoe de vyanden van En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghel-landt alle middel ſoecken om de Coninginne end de goede, onderſaeten te ouervallen ende te verdrucken om dat ſy door alſulcke aenſlaghen ſouden moghen den crijchſ-handel voorderen die van de Capiteynen der In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitien gheu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ert wordt in de Neder-landen teghen de goede Landiſ-ſaeten: Weiende voor ſeker / dat alle de ve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaederinghe die-men in Spanien maect onder t'vedeckſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> van t'Coninck-rijck van Poortegael te benechten / ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghens elders toe en ſtreckt / dan tot duſdanighen eynde. Godt door ſyne gratie verleene der Coninghinnen een lanck leuen / ende beſcherme haer van alle ſulcken bedriechelijcken voortſtel / op dat Godts ende haere vyandengheen oorſaecke en crijghen om haerlieder bloetghierighe heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchappie te verbreyden.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <add>Te London, int jaer M.D.Lxxix.</add>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5862:3"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
